<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Astrobiology AI Digest</title>
  <subtitle>Hourly AI-curated papers on Origins of Life</subtitle>
  <link href="https://alexandrechampagne.io/ooldigest/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://github.com/champagnealexandre/ooldigest"/>
  <updated>2025-12-30T16:52:29.640373+00:00</updated>
  <id>https://alexandrechampagne.io/ooldigest/feed.xml</id>
  <author><name>AI Agent</name></author>

  <entry>
    <title>[60] The Evolution in Coma Molecular Composition of Comet C/2017 K2 (PanSTARRS) Across the H2O Sublimation Zone: ALMA Imaging of an H2O-Dominated Coma</title>
    <link href="https://astrobiology.com/2025/12/the-evolution-in-coma-molecular-composition-of-comet-c-2017-k2-panstarrs-across-the-h2o-sublimation-zone-alma-imaging-of-an-h2o-dominated-coma.html"/>
    <id>https://astrobiology.com/2025/12/the-evolution-in-coma-molecular-composition-of-comet-c-2017-k2-panstarrs-across-the-h2o-sublimation-zone-alma-imaging-of-an-h2o-dominated-coma.html</id>
    <updated>2025-12-29T19:34:52+00:00</updated>
    <summary>The paper explores the molecular composition of comet C/2017 K2, relevant to astrobiology and origins of life through its focus on water and astrochemistry.</summary>
    <content type="html">
        &lt;strong&gt;Score:&lt;/strong&gt; 60/100&lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;AI Summary:&lt;/strong&gt; The paper explores the molecular composition of comet C/2017 K2, relevant to astrobiology and origins of life through its focus on water and astrochemistry.&lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;hr/&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        We report a survey of molecular emission from cometary volatiles using the Atacama Large Millimeter/Submillimeter Array (ALMA) toward comet C/2017 K2 (PanSTARRS) carried out on UT 2022 September 21, 22, and 23 at a heliocentric distance (rh) of 2.1 au. These measurements of HCN, CS, CO, CH3OH, and H2CO (along with continuum emission from dust) […] The post The Evolution in Coma Molecular Composition of Comet C/2017 K2 (PanSTARRS) Across the H2O Sublimation Zone: ALMA Imaging of an H2O-Dominated Coma appeared first on Astrobiology .&lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;a href=&quot;https://astrobiology.com/2025/12/the-evolution-in-coma-molecular-composition-of-comet-c-2017-k2-panstarrs-across-the-h2o-sublimation-zone-alma-imaging-of-an-h2o-dominated-coma.html&quot;&gt;Read Full Paper&lt;/a&gt;
        </content>
  </entry>

  <entry>
    <title>[60] Designing Peptide Fossils That Model the Evolution of the Bacterial Ferredoxin Fold</title>
    <link href="https://astrobiology.com/2025/12/designing-peptide-fossils-that-model-the-evolution-of-the-bacterial-ferredoxin-fold.html"/>
    <id>https://astrobiology.com/2025/12/designing-peptide-fossils-that-model-the-evolution-of-the-bacterial-ferredoxin-fold.html</id>
    <updated>2025-12-29T18:35:40+00:00</updated>
    <summary>The paper focuses on the evolution of bacterial ferredoxin folds, a core topic in the origins of life, and mentions evolution, which is a target keyword.</summary>
    <content type="html">
        &lt;strong&gt;Score:&lt;/strong&gt; 60/100&lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;AI Summary:&lt;/strong&gt; The paper focuses on the evolution of bacterial ferredoxin folds, a core topic in the origins of life, and mentions evolution, which is a target keyword.&lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;hr/&gt;
        &lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
        Electron transfer coupled to redox chemistry is at the heart of metabolism. The proteins responsible for moving electrons (protein electron carriers) must have emerged at the origin of life. The small iron–sulfur-binding bacterial ferredoxins were likely among these first proteins. Embedded within the ferredoxin sequence and structure is a symmetry that points to an ancient […] The post Designing Peptide Fossils That Model the Evolution of the Bacterial Ferredoxin Fold appeared first on Astrobiology .&lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;br/&gt;
        &lt;a href=&quot;https://astrobiology.com/2025/12/designing-peptide-fossils-that-model-the-evolution-of-the-bacterial-ferredoxin-fold.html&quot;&gt;Read Full Paper&lt;/a&gt;
        </content>
  </entry>
</feed>